Good morning. Today's דף daf is ק''יב, Kuf Yud Bet, בבא קמא
Bava Kamma 112, and we pick up at the bottom of ק''יא
Kuf Yud Aleph עמוד ב, Amud Bet, and it's אמר מר, Amar
Mar, and I should say that I am recording this דף daf
during the שבעה Shiva for my nephew Maoz Morel who passed away
on Monday, died defending עם ישראל Am Yisrael ומדינת ישראל u-Medinat Yisrael
as a paratrooper in this horrific war that we've been fighting since
October 7th, and may this learning be in his memory and לעילוי
נשמתו. le-iluy nishmato. Okay, we pick up three lines from the bottom
on ק''יא Kuf Yud Aleph עמוד ב, Amud Bet, אמר מר, Amar
Mar, and we're dealing with this issue about the משנה Mishna about
הגוזל ומאכיל, ha-gozel u-ma'akhil, somebody who steals and feeds to his sons,
or then leaves the אבדה aveda for his children. And the משנה
Mishna says that they are פטור, patur, but if it's something of
אחריות נכסים achrayut nechasim they are חייב. chayav. And a little vague
what אחריות נכסים achrayut nechasim means, and we actually have two key
positions that we're working off of in this whole discussion: the position
of רב חסדא Rav Chisda that if somebody damages or eats somebody
else's stolen object before יאוש, ye'ush, they're obligated to pay, so גזל
ולא נתייאשו הבעלים ובא אחר ואכלו רצה מזה גובה ורצה מזה גובה.
gezel ve-lo nityaeishu ha-be'alim u-ba acher ve-akhalo ratza mi-ze gove ve-ratza mi-ze
gove. So that's one position, which means that the case in the
משנה Mishna where גוזל ומאכיל את בניו gozel u-ma'akhil et banav that
the children are פטור patur has to be for him a case
of after יאוש. ye'ush. So that's one key position, whether when the
second party comes and eats and consumes it are they פטור patur
even before יאוש ye'ush or only after יאוש. ye'ush. The second key
position that we're dealing with is the position of רמי בר חמא
Rami bar Chama who says that, which is the position that רשות
יורש כרשות לוקח דמי. reshut yoresh ke-reshut loke'ach dami. When somebody inherits
something, is it considered like a שינוי רשות? shinui reshut? And that's
relevant for the second part of the משנה, Mishna, which is הניח
לפניהם פטורים לשלם, hiniach lifneichem peturim le-shalem, that if the father leaves
it in front of them they're פטור. patur. And the simple sense
of the משנה Mishna is that we are talking about something that
is הגזילה בעין, ha-gezeila be-ein, that the object is still around, and
nevertheless they don't have to return it. What's the logic? How could
it be they don't have to return the object if it's still
around? And for this, רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama says well,
because it's a שינוי רשות shinui reshut and we would be talking
about after יאוש ye'ush and therefore they would be פטור. patur. So
again, the question first of all is why are they פטור patur
in the first part of the משנה Mishna for eating it? Could
be before יאוש ye'ush and the owner does not have a strong
enough ownership to obligate them, or according to רב חסדא Rav Chisda
only after יאוש. ye'ush. Why are they פטור patur in the second
part of the משנה? Mishna? That would be because it's after יאוש
ye'ush and רשות יורש כרשות לוקח. reshut yoresh ke-reshut loke'ach. And if
you don't agree to either of those, either that it's talking after
יאוש ye'ush or that רשות יורש כרשות לוקח, reshut yoresh ke-reshut loke'ach,
you would have to explain the reason they're פטור patur in the
second part of the משנה Mishna is that they actually consumed the
גזילה, gezeila, it is not בעין. be-ein. Then the only difference is
whether they ate it in the life of their father or after
the life of the father. So those are the two key positions,
רב חסדא Rav Chisda and רמי בר חמא. Rami bar Chama. Now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר מר, Amar Mar, we are
now five lines from the
bottom, six lines from the bottom, two words before the end of
the line in ק''יא Kuf Yud Aleph עמוד ב. Amud Bet. And
we're looking at the ברייתא Braita of רבי אושעיא, Rabbi Oshaya, and
the ברייתא Braita of רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya made it clear that
when the גזילה gezeila was קיימת, kayemet, they had to return it.
So let's take a look. אמר מר אין הגזילה קיימת
פטורים, Amar Mar ein ha-gezeila kayemet peturim,
when the גזילה gezeila is no longer around, it's been consumed, they're
פטור. patur. So
לימא תהוי תיובתא דרב חסדא, leima tehevei tiyuvta de-Rav Chisda, let's say
this is a contradiction of רב חסדא Rav Chisda because maybe we
would be talking about all cases even before יאוש. ye'ush. אמר לך
רב חסדא כי תניא היא לאחר יאוש. Amar lakh Rav Chisda ki
tanya hi le-achar ye'ush. We're talking about after יאוש. ye'ush. Okay, just
like the משנה, Mishna, the case of the משנה Mishna where if
they ate it they're פטור patur is after יאוש. ye'ush. אמר מר
גזילה קיימת חייבים לשלם. Amar Mar gezeila kayemet chayavim le-shalem. Now let's
look at the second part. Again, this is the ברייתא Braita which
is also the simple sense of the משנה. Mishna. If the גזילה
gezeila is still around, they have to pay. לימא תהוי תיובתא דרמי
בר חמא, leima tehevei tiyuvta de-Rami bar Chama, let's say that would
be a problem on רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama because he
said that
רשות יורש כרשות לוקח דמי. reshut yoresh ke-reshut loke'ach dami. And this
is not like the משנה. Mishna. The משנה Mishna says that even
if it was around they're פטור patur to give it back and
that is רמי בר חמא, Rami bar Chama, יאוש ושינוי רשות. ye'ush
ve-shinui reshut. But the ברייתא Braita of רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya says
that if the גזילה gezeila is around they have to give it
back. Isn't that a contradiction to רמי בר חמא? Rami bar Chama?
We don't say יאוש ושינוי רשות, ye'ush ve-shinui reshut, that רשות יורש
reshut yoresh is not like רשות לוקח? reshut loke'ach? אמר לך רמי
בר חמא, Amar lakh Rami bar Chama, רמי בר חמא Rami bar
Chama would say to you: כי תניא היא לפני יאוש. ki tanya
hi lifnei ye'ush. Okay, top of ק''יב Kuf Yud Bet עמוד א.
Amud Aleph. No, we're talking about before יאוש. ye'ush. All right, so
an argument that you have to pay when they eat it or
don't have to pay is the question of is the exemption when
they consume it even before יאוש ye'ush or only after יאוש. ye'ush.
or only לאחר יאוש, le'achar yeush, רב חסדא Rav Chisda would say
only לאחר יאוש. le'achar yeush. And then the question about do they
have to return it if it's בעין, be'ayn, a possible difference between
the משנה Mishnah that sounds like they don't return it and the
ברייתא Braita that says they do could be the question of whether
רשות יורש כרשות לוקח reshut yoresh k'reshut lokeach or not, and we'd
be talking after יאוש. yeush. But could it be debated whether it's
considered a שינוי רשות? shinui reshut? Or it could be according to
רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama the difference before, before יאוש yeush
and after יאוש. yeush. After יאוש yeush it's יאוש ושינוי רשות, yeush
v'shinui reshut, רשות יורש כרשות לוקח. reshut yoresh k'reshut lokeach. Before יאוש
yeush obviously it does not matter and they would have to return.
Okay, רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava מתני להא דרמי
בר חמא. masni l'ha d'Rami bar Chama. Now רב אדא בר אהבה
Rav Adda bar Ahava taught the teaching of רמי בר חמא Rami
bar Chama that רשות יורש כרשות לוקח reshut yoresh k'reshut lokeach אהא
aha on the following ברייתא. Braita. הניח להם אביהם מעות של ריבית,
heniach lahem avihem maot shel ribit, not a case of the father
leaving over the גזילה, gezeila, but the father leaving over money that
he got by charging interest. Now again, money when you charge money
in interest, the person is actually willingly paying it. It's just forbidden
to charge it and to collect it and to pay it. And
it's not even clear that you would have to give it back.
I mean, you transgressed, but ultimately the person willingly paid it. We're
going to see that the גמרא Gemara is going to learn from
a פסוק passuk that the money has to be given back. So
what happens though if this money, this interest money was bequeathed to
the children, the person died? So אף על פי שיודעים שהן של
ריבית, af al pi sheyodim shehen shel ribit, even though the children
know that this is money that was earned through charging interest, אין
חייבים להחזיר. ein chayavim lehachzir. They don't have an obligation to return
it. It's not stolen. Fine. אמר רמי בר חמא זאת אומרת רשות
יורש כרשות לוקח דמי. Amar Rami bar Chama zot omeret reshut yoresh
k'reshut lokeach dami. So רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama said, it's
obvious to me that if it was still considered to be in
the possession of the father, then you would have to give it
back. So this is not an issue of like יאוש ושינוי רשות,
yeush v'shinui reshut, that's not what we're talking about, but what we're
talking about is
that it's no longer under seen as still within the father's estate.
It's now owned by the children. It's a different possession and therefore
it doesn't have to be given back. But if it was considered
to be a kind of continuity, then it would have to be
given back.
Okay.
רבא Rava אמר, רבא Amar Rava, says, לעולם אימא לך רשות יורש
לאו כרשות לוקח דמי. le'olam eima lecha reshut yoresh lav k'reshut lokeach
dami. I could really tell you
that
the רשות reshut of the יורש yoresh is not considered like a
purchaser and is a continuation of the father's possession and domain. But
okay, but then so therefore why wouldn't the kids have to give
it back? ושאני הכא דאמר קרא v'shani hacha d'amar kra because let's
look at the פסוק passuk that actually is the basis of giving
back ריבית ribit money. The פסוק passuk says אל תקח מאתו נשך
ותרבית, al tikach me'ito neshech v'tarbit, do not take from him ריבית,
ribit, two different words for ריבית. ribit. אהדריה ליה ahadreih leih and
from that we read כי היכי ki heichi and the end of
the פסוק passuk is וחי אחיך עמך, v'chai achicha imach, your brother
should live with you. אהדריה ליה, ahadreih leih, give it back to
him, כי היכי דניחי בהדך, ki heichi d'nichi bahadach, that in order
that he should live together with you. So it's really funny. There's
no real clear פסוק passuk you give the ריבית ribit back, but
from וחי אחיך עמך, v'chai achicha imach, חז"ל Chazal learn that there's
an idea to try to restore the balance and to give it
back. All right, but that's not like it's not your money and
it's a stolen
object. It's כי היכי דניחי בהדך, ki heichi d'nichi bahadach, that you
should live well together. So לדידיה קמזהר ליה רחמנא, l'didei k'mazhar leih
rachmana, the תורה Torah is commanding the person that lent the money,
לבריה לא קמזהר ליה רחמנא, livrei lo k'mazhar leih rachmana, not to
the son. So the basic idea being that this is a personal
obligation of the one who charged interest. It's not like the money
is ill-gotten gains and therefore as long as it hasn't gone out
of his possession,
you have to give it back. That might be a question of
רשות יורש כרשות לוקח reshut yoresh k'reshut lokeach or not. No, he
actually, it's his money, it was freely given to him, the person
who charged interest. But he has an obligation to restore the situation,
a personal obligation, and it only applies to him and not to
his children. Okay.
That
is how this issue of returning the ריבית ribit might have nothing
to do with the issue about whether the children,
רשות יורש reshut yoresh is רשות לוקח, reshut lokeach, even if it's
all considered to be like the money still is in the same
domain and under the same ownership. But still the obligation is only
a personal one on the person who actually charged ריבית. ribit. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara is just going to, now we have two
understandings of where רמי בר חמא's Rami bar Chama teaching was applied
to, whether it was applied to our משנה, Mishnah, whether it was
applied to the ברייתא. Braita. Now the גמרא Gemara is going to
discuss whether one implies the other or not. So let's take a
look. מאן דמתני לה אברייתא כל שכן אמתניתין. man d'masni lah a'baraita
kol sheken a'matnitin. If you apply the principle of רשות יורש כרשות
לוקח reshut yoresh k'reshut lokeach to the ברייתא Braita about the idea
of returning ריבית, ribit, then you would certainly apply it to the
משנה. Mishnah. Now why is not so clear, what רש"י Rashi says
is because the simple sense of the משנה Mishnah is that the
גזילה gezeila is still around בעין, be'ayn, הניח לפניהם. heniach lifneihem.
So the only reasonable explanation of that משנה Mishnah is יאוש ושינוי
רשות yeush v'shinui reshut which is רשות יורש כרשות לוקח. reshut yoresh
k'reshut lokeach. So the ברייתא Braita doesn't need... this fancy idea of
רשות יורש כרשות לוקח; reshus yoresh ke-reshus lokeach; it could just be
that the whole obligation of ריבית ribis is only on the person
who charged it. So if you're gonna introduce the idea on the
ברייתא, braisa, then you would certainly apply it to the משנה; mishnah;
the משנה mishnah is much more cause for this principle. אבל מאן
דמתני לה אמתניתין, Aval man de-masni lei a-masnisin, but if you teach
it on the משנה mishnah where again, it's really, you understand why
it's necessary because the simple sense of the משנה mishnah is that
the גזילה gezeilah is בעין, be-ein, so it only makes sense with
יאוש ושינוי רשות yei'ush ve-shinui reshus that you don't have to return
it. אבל אברייתא רמי בר חמא כרבא מתני לה, Aval a-braisa Rami
bar Chama ke-Rava masni lah, but when it comes to this ברייתא
braisa about about ריבית ribis that might have nothing to do with
רשות יורש כרשות לוקח. reshus yoresh ke-reshus lokeach. It fundamentally the ריבית
ribis money is yours, is the belongs to the person who charged
interest, you know, even though he violated, and the idea to return
it is just a personal obligation on him and not on his
children. Okay, so those are different ways of understanding where רמי בר
חמא's Rami bar Chama teaching was said in reference to what. תנו
רבנן. Tano rabanan. And now we're still going to be working with
these two ideas of רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama and primarily
also of רב חסדא Rav Chisda about when the children are obligated
or not obligated if they eat the גזילה gezeilah that the father
left them before or after יאוש. yei'ush. תנו רבנן הגוזל ומאכיל את
בניו פטורים מלשלם. Tano rabanan, ha-gozel u-ma'achil es banav peturin li-shaleim.
Somebody who stole and fed it to the kids, they're exempt from
paying. That's okay, that's the first part of our משנה. mishnah. הניח
לפניהם, Hiniach lifneihem, if it was left in front of them and
this again, the simple meaning here is that the גזילה gezeilah is
בעין, be-ein, that the object is still around, גדולים חייבים לשלם קטנים
פטורים מלשלם. gedolim chayavin li-shaleim ketanim peturin li-shaleim. The adult children
if they're adult children they have to return it, if they're minors
they don't. So let's first talk about why the adults have to
return it. Well, it's בעין, be-ein, and you know, if you hold
רשות יורש reshus yoresh is like רשות לוקח, reshus lokeach, then it
would be before יאוש, yei'ush, okay? That there's always a reason to
return it if it's בעין. be-ein. Either it's before יאוש yei'ush or
it's after יאוש yei'ush and you hold רשות יורש reshus yoresh is
not like רשות לוקח, reshus lokeach, so there's no שינוי רשות. shinui
reshus. But one way or another there's always a scenario where you'll
have to return it בעין be-ein and that's when the adult children
have to, but not the minor children. Why not? Because even though
it's my object, you know, it's like a, you know, it's my
iPhone there that is sitting in this person's house and he died
and his minor children now but now are around but but it's
my iPhone; why can't I go and take it? So that's going
to be the principle of מקבלים עדות שלא בפני בעל דין. mekabelin
eidus she-lo bifnei ba'al din. I still would have to bring it
to court to prove that it was my iPhone and therefore I
cannot do that if I cannot if, you know, the person I'm
bringing the testimony against is not able to defend himself. So the
same way if the person wasn't around, you know, person has a
right to face their accuser, you know, you couldn't proceed with a
court case without there being present. We'll see exceptions about that coming
up. But similarly if the other side are minors, that also is
not fair and you would have to wait till they become adults.
So that's why as minors they do not have to give it
back, we will have the court case when they grow up. ואם
אמרו
גדולים, Ve-im amru gedolim,
now in the case of the adult children, if they say איננו
יודעים חשבונות שחישב אבינו עמך, einanu yod'in cheshbonos she-chishiv avinu imach, we
don't know the arrangement that our father made with you; it's true
that this stolen object is in our possession, but you know, maybe
he paid you for it and maybe you allowed him to keep
it. So in that case פטורים, peturin, then in that case they
would be exempt.
So
פטורים מלשלם, peturin li-shaleim, they don't have to פטורים, peturin, they're exempt.
So the גמרא Gemara questions this: משום דאמרי אין אנו יודעים פטורים?
mishum de-amri ein anu yod'in peturin? Wait, because they say we don't
know that exempts them? You definitely have this stolen object in their
home, my iPhone is sitting in their home, because they say well
maybe my father made a deal with you, how does that get
them out of it? It's definitely my iPhone, prove it if you
want to keep it. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא Rava reinterprets
this: הכי קאמר גדולים שאמרו יודעין אנו חשבונות שחישב אבינו עמך ולא
פשעת לך גבאי ולא מידי פטורים. hachi ka-amar gedolim she-amru yod'in anu
cheshbonos she-chishiv avinu imach ve-lo pashat lach gabai ve-lo midei peturin. If
the children say we actually do know that our father made an
arrangement and that he paid you for it, in that case they
are exempt because still it's המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, hamotzi me-chaveiro alav
ha-rayah, possession is nine-tenths of the law. So even though I could
prove it used to be my iPhone, now it is in their
possession, and if, you know, if I could prove but you know,
you know, my iPhone used to be mine and it's in your
possession and you say you bought it from me, you would be
believed. So here too, I say the father stole it and the
kids say yeah but we bought it, and so the kids are
going to be believed. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this:
Okay,
תניא אידך, tanya idach, we taught in another ברייתא: braisa: הגוזל ומאכיל
בניו פטורים מלשלם, ha-gozel u-ma'achil banav peturin li-shaleim, somebody who steals and
feeds to the kids they're exempt, okay, that we know first part
of our משנה. mishnah. הניח לפניהם
ואכלום, Hiniach lifneihem ve-achalum, if he left it in front of them
and they consumed it, בין גדולים בין קטנים חייבים, bein gedolim bein
ketanim chayavin, whether adults or minors they're obligated. Now this is quite
strange. So the גמרא Gemara says קטנים מי מחייבי? ketanim mi-mechayvei? Because
here it's not that the גזילה gezeilah is בעין, be-ein, it's been
destroyed. So the only way that the children would have to pay
is that they've incurred obligation, it's not the obligation of their father.
So the גמרא Gemara says, how could minors be obligated? obligated if
they went ahead and they ate this גזילה. gezeila. ולא יהא אלא
דאזיק אזוקי, Velo yehei ela de'azik azuki, if a minor went ahead
and damaged property you're exempt. There's no liability for a minor, right?
It's not my object is בעינא be'eina and I'm trying to retrieve
it. It's not the obligation of the father. This actually I'm trying
to make the minor pay for eating it, but they don't have
any liability. So this makes absolutely no sense the way we taught
it. So אמר רב פפא הכי קאמר, Amar Rav Papa hachi ka'amar,
here's how you have to read this ברייתא: braita: הניח לפניהם ועדיין
לא אכלום. Hiniach lifneihem ve'adayin lo achlum. The word אכלום achlum is
basically a mistake. Okay, it means it's still around and they haven't
eaten it. So it's exactly like the previous ברייתא. braita. If the
father fed it to them, they're exempt. If the גזילה gezeila still
around, then this ברייתא braita teaches: בין גדולים ובין קטנים חייבים, bein
gedolim uvein ktanim chayavim,
whether adults or minors they're obligated. So as opposed to the previous
ברייתא braita that said when it's still around minors are not obligated,
this says minors are obligated. So we will see, this is a
debate of whether you can accept testimony, at least in some cases,
not in the presence of בעל דין ba'al din or when the
בעל דין ba'al din is a minor. Okay, but we're all talking
about the גזילה gezeila is around and that is the issue at
stake here.
Okay, אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא: Rava הניח להם אביהם פרה
שאולה, hiniach lahem avihem para she'ula, we're now at the last of
the narrow lines, their father left in front of them a borrowed
cow. The father borrowed the cow and they are aware of this.
משתמשים בו כל ימי שאילתה. Mishtamshin bo kol yemei she'elata. So when
the borrower bothers it, let's say he borrowed it for a year,
he made an arrangement and then he died, so he basically has
the rights to use it for a year. And one way to
think of borrowing is a מתנה לגוף לפירות לזמן. matana leguf laperos
lizman. The same way I can gift you something or I can
actually gift you something for a limited period of time, I could
also gift you its use for a limited period of time, that's
what a שאילה she'eila is. So he would inherit those rights he
has to use that object to his children. מתה אין חייבים באונסה.
Meisa ein chayavim be'onsa. But this is very interesting, if the cow
dies, not due to any fault of their own, it drops dead.
As a normal שואל sho'el you are obligated even באונסין, be'onsin, even
if the object gets destroyed not due to any fault of your
own. But here this ברייתא braita is assuming that that obligation is
assumed only by the person who borrowed it. So the property rights
to the object can be passed down. The same way when a
father dies the children inherit the property he owns, when the father
dies the children have the property rights he has in this cow.
But the obligation to pay is a personal obligation assumed by the
father and not by the children, so they actually would be exempt.
Now, כסבורים של אביהם היא, kesvurim shel avihem hi, they let's say
they didn't realize that it was borrowed and they assumed it was
their father's. You know, it was just a cow that the father
had had around, what did they know that it was borrowed? וטבחוה
ואכלוה, Utvachua ve'achlua,
and they slaughtered it and ate it, משלמים דמי בשר בזול. meshalmin
dmei basar bezol. They pay for cheap meat. Meaning you figure out
how much the meat was actually worth in the open market and
they would pay, as רש''י Rashi points out they pay
two thirds of the cost. Now what's the logic here? The logic
is well we already said they're not חייב chayav because of a
שואל, sho'el, they didn't assume the obligation. How about make them obligated
as a מזיק, mazik, they slaughtered this guy's cow and they ate
it? But they did not do it intentionally to damage. And not
only that, we've learned like אדם מועד לעולם. adam muad le'olam. If
somebody slipped and broke something you also didn't intentionally damage and he
has to go ahead and pay for it. But in this case
their relationship to it was that's still knowing that it's somebody else's
object and accidentally breaking it, okay? Or being negligent. I borrowed your
object and I forgot and I thought it was mine. All those
cases it starts with the idea that my relationship to it was
as an other and therefore when I break it I'm a מזיק.
mazik. In this case they had all the rights to assume it
was their father's. It was on their property when their father died
and therefore their relationship to it was like they ate it with
permission as it were, or not certainly as a מזיק mazik and
therefore the only thing that you can make them pay for is
the benefit that they received. So not the actual market value of
the meat, but they got a nice full meal. So the way
you assess what's the benefit of a full meal is this somehow
this sort of calculus of paying two thirds of the value. That's
the principle there. Okay, now: הניח להם אביהם אחריות נכסים חייבים לשלם.
hiniach lahem avihem achrayus nechasim chayavim leshalem.
If their father left them property that has liens on it, then
they have to pay. Now the גמרא Gemara is going to ask
which case this goes on. איכא דמתני לה ארישא ואיכא דמתני לה
אסיפא. Ika dmatni la'reisha ve'ika dmatni la'seifa. Some apply this to the
first case when it was borrowed and then something happened to it,
the question of חיוב אונסין chiyuv onsin by a שאילה. she'eila. And
some teach it about the last case about when they slaughtered it
and ate it. So let's take a look. מן דמתני לה ארישא
כל שכן אסיפא ופליגא דרב פפא. Man dmatni la'reisha kol sheken seifa
upliga derav papa. Now
the one who teaches it on the first case of שואל sho'el
which of when an accident happened or the cow just dropped dead.
would certainly apply it to the last case and argues on רב
פפא. Rav Pappa. Let's just read this and then we'll explain what
all this means. ומן דמתני לה אסיפא, u'man d'masni la aseifa,
but if you only teach it about the last case about eating
slaughtering it and eating it, אבל ארישא לא, aval areisha lo, but
when in the first case about the about it died you would
not be obligated even if the father left real estate, why? והיינו
דרב פפא, v'hainu d'Rav Pappa, because
that would be consistent with רב פפא. Rav Pappa. So we'll just
read רב פפא Rav Pappa and then we'll go back and explain
all of this. דאמר רב פפא, d'amar Rav Pappa, because רב פפא
Rav Pappa says: האי פרה גנובה לו וטבחה בשבת חייב hai para
genuva lo u'tavcha b'shabbos chayav שכבר נתחייב בגנבה קודם שבא לידי איסור
שבת. shekevar nischayev b'gneiva kodem sheba l'yedei issur shabbos.
So the principle is you can't do something, if you do an
act that's חייב מיתה, chayav misa, then you don't incur monetary obligations
that come together with that act. That's a principle of קים ליה
בדרבה מיניה. kam lei b'drabba minei. So if somebody had stolen a
cow before שבת Shabbos and on שבת Shabbos he slaughtered it, and
we'll remember that גנבה gneiva with טביחה tivicha is חייב chayav four
or five, then you have to actually pay the four or five,
why? שכבר נתחייב בגנבה קודם שבא לידי איסור שבת. shekevar nischayev b'gneiva
kodem sheba l'yedei issur shabbos. The obligation of the principal and the
כפל kefel came when you stole it on Thursday, and the fact
that now you slaughtered it and now you have to pay, you
know, go from two to four to five, that's a קנס, knas,
the four or five. And the principle is actually you can pay
a קנס, knas, a קנס knas that you incurred because a קנס
knas is a חידוש, chiddush, a קנס knas that you incur a
monetary fine you can be obligated even even when you're חייב מיתה,
chayav misa, even when you do an act that's חייב מיתה. chayav
misa. We don't say קים ליה kam lei by a קנס. knas.
So that case you would pay four or five.
However, האי פרה שאולה לו, hai para she'ula lo, now we're getting
to what's relevant to us, if the guy had borrowed the cow
on a Thursday וטבחה בשבת u'tavcha b'shabbos and slaughtered it on שבת,
Shabbos, פטור, patur, in that case you're exempt, שאיסור שבת ואיסור גנבה
באים כאחד, she'issur shabbos v'issur gneiva ba'im k'echad,
because the איסור שבת issur shabbos and the stealing it through the
slaughtering it came at the same time. Okay, so what does this
mean? So you're not going to be חייב chayav here anyway for
four or five, it's not a, there's never really a גנבה, gneiva,
okay, it started off as a שאילה. she'ila. So the question though
is why aren't you חייב chayav when you slaughter it on שבת?
Shabbos? So forget גנבה gneiva and that. Why aren't you חייב chayav
when you slaughter on שבת Shabbos for מזיק? mazik? Well, you're not
חייב chayav for מזיק mazik or call it גנבה gneiva or whatever,
but anyway it's not a גנבה gneiva and then a שחיטה, sh'chita,
the שחיטה sh'chita might be the גנבה. gneiva. But anyway, why are
you not חייב chayav for that? You're not חייב chayav because that's
a monetary obligation that comes at the time that you did a
חילול שבת. chillul shabbos. So that's why you're not חייב chayav for
the שחיטה. sh'chita. Great. None of that is relevant to us. What's
relevant to us is that רב פפא Rav Pappa is also saying
you're not חייב chayav as a שואל. shoel. Remember you borrowed it
on Thursday, on שבת Shabbos it died. Let's forget about the fact
that you slaughtered it. Fine, you have no חיוב chiuv for מזיק
mazik or for גנבה gneiva on שבת, Shabbos, it happened through חילול
שבת. chillul shabbos. Fine, nothing. But pay because you're a שואל shoel
and the cow that you borrowed died. So the fact that he
says you don't have to pay shows that רב פפא Rav Pappa
says that the obligation of the שואל shoel comes when the damage
happens, not when the object was borrowed. You borrowed an object on
Thursday, it died on שבת. Shabbos. When do you become when do
we say your obligations, you know, to do restitution began? So the
easiest thing is to say what רב פפא Rav Pappa said: when
it when it dies you assume the obligation at that moment that
it died on שבת, Shabbos, that's when you're obligated. Oh, okay, but
that came at the time of חילול שבת, chillul shabbos, so קים
ליה בדרבה מיניה. kam lei b'drabba minei. What's, how would you say
the other way? The other way you would say it's actually quite
simple. You would say: when you borrowed the cow you assumed the
obligation to return the cow. That obligation, when I borrowed from ראובן
Reuven a cow on Thursday, on Thursday I now owe ראובן Reuven
a cow. If the cow is still alive and I return it,
I exempt myself from the obligation. If the cow died, died on
שבת, Shabbos, I don't care when the cow died, my obligation to
pay him started on Thursday, I just can't exempt myself from it
because the cow's already dead. So that's the position that argues on
רב פפא. Rav Pappa. So the question of רב פפא Rav Pappa
is: when is a שואל shoel obligated when something happens to the
object? The moment that it happens to the object or from the
moment it was borrowed? How is all of this relevant to us?
Well, that was a lot. Okay, now we have to go back
and figure out how it's relevant to us. Because the father borrowed
the cow and he had real estate. The real estate would have
liens on it and now he died and the kids, and and
then after he died the cow died. Does can the person who
lent him the cow collect from the real estate? So it depends:
when did the obligation begin? If the obligation began when the father
was around, not like רב פפא, Rav Pappa, when the cow was
borrowed, then at the moment the father borrowed the cow the owner
of the cow got liens on the father's
property. the kids are not חייב chayav in אונסין. onesin. It doesn't
matter, I have liens already against the father's estate for the cow
for when the father was alive and and there that estate, that
property is still there, I will collect my liens from the property.
So that is how you could teach the משנה Mishna that if
the father left real estate which has liens, then then the children
do have to pay, you could teach it on the first case
about the borrowed cow that died if you disagree with רב פפא.
Rav Pappa. And if you say that a obligation of the borrower
begins from the moment it's borrowed. Okay, that's how you would teach
it at the first part of the משנה, Mishna, you would actually
reject רב פפא. Rav Pappa. However, if you agree with רב פפא,
Rav Pappa, then even in that scenario where the father borrowed it
and there was real estate, there were no liens on the property,
there was no obligation until the cow died, and therefore when the
cow died, it was only the kids. So and and the kids
didn't assume the obligation. So if you agree with רב פפא, Rav
Pappa, the father leaving real estate would not obligate them when the
cow dies. And you would only teach this issue of אחריות achrayus
matters in the second case. And the second case is when they
thought it was their father's and they slaughtered it. Now we have
to explain that. Okay, so the question about the first case about
when the cow dies, does that matter if the father left real
estate, that depends whether the obligation begins at the moment of borrowing
or at the moment that the damage happens. But everybody agrees that
this principle of אחריות achrayus would explain the would be relevant to
the second case of the משנה, Mishna, when the kids thought it
belonged to their father and they slaughtered it and they ate it.
If the father left them property, then they don't pay two-thirds of
the cost, then they pay the full cost. And it's really not
at all clear what leaving property has to do with it, right?
There's no liens on the property when he borrowed it, we already
said that. So what the heck does if they slaughtered it and
ate it, do they pay full cost or two-thirds, have to do
with leaving property? רש״י Rashi makes it sound like it's a question
of how much do we see the children as a continuation of
the father, sort of like רשות יורש כרשות לוקח. reshus yoresh kereshus
lokeiach. But in this action of slaughtering it and eating it, if
the father, for example, forgot that it was borrowed and slaughtered it
and ate it, we'd call him a מזיק. mazik. You have a
responsibility to remember that it's borrowed. Okay, and you don't, you destroyed
somebody's object, you have to pay for it. So the kids, do
they see them as a continuation of the father? Well, if there's
real estate, then we sort of that again this just shows a
sense of continuity and so on and you know with real estate,
then we see them as a continuation in the same way the
father would be obligated they would be, but if there's not real
estate, then we see it as a new פרשה parsha and therefore
they are פטור. pattur. All right, that was a lot of stuff
there about this question about the borrowed cow. Now we are finally
going to go back to the earlier issue about if the גזילה
gezeilah is בעין be'ein and whether you can collect it from the
קטנים ketanim or not. So let's take a look.
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, a
rabbis taught: והשיב את הגזילה אשר גזל, Veheishiv es hagezeilah asher gazal,
you should return the גזילה gezeilah that you stole. If you remember
that was of course the the פסוק passuk we quoted earlier for
the principle of שינוי. shinui. מה תלמוד לומר אשר גזל, Mah talmud
lomar asher gazal, what is that idea "that you stole" teaching? יחזיר
כעין שגזל, Yachzir k'ein shegazal,
that you have to turn it return it if it's around the
way it was stolen. מכאן אמרו, Mikan amru, from here they said:
הגוזל ומאכיל את בניו פטורים מלשלם, Hagozel uma'achil es banav peturim milishalem,
that one who steals and and feeds his kids is exempt from
paying. So this is interesting that you know what exactly the principle
is this teaching us. תוספות Tosafos says, you know, this works better
not like רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. That this is like רב חסדא,
Rav Chisda, the גמרא Gemara said what's the reason for רב חסדא,
Rav Chisda, that it's only after יאוש. yeiush. Well because it happened
after יאוש, yeiush, you know, therefore you don't really have control over
it and therefore when it gets consumed after יאוש, yeiush, the second
party is not obligated. But here it just says no, the פסוק
passuk says only when it's still around. So what does that mean,
you only return it when it's still in the original form? It
can't mean for the גזלן gazlan himself. גזלן Gazlan himself even if
it's destroyed has to pay back. Ah, but for his kids, the
פסוק passuk is teaching you that if it's not around, they don't
have to pay it back. Okay, that they don't even even if
they were the ones that ate it, that is not considered to
be חייב chayav not as a גזלן, gazlan, not as a מזיק,
mazik, and they would be פטור. pattur. So it's nice to use
that פסוק passuk to explain the משנה Mishna that you're פטור, pattur,
the kids are exempt even if they ate it before יאוש, yeiush,
not like רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, we have a special פסוק passuk
that teaches us that. Okay, but that's the first part of the
משנה. Mishna. Now הניח לפניהם בין גדולים בין קטנים, Hiniach lifneihem bein
gedolim bein ketanim, and now we are finally going to get back
to this question about it being בעין. be'ein. If it was in
front of them, if he left it to them and בעין, be'ein,
whether they're adults or children, חייבים, chayavim, they're obligated. משום סומכוס אמרו,
Mishum Sumchos amru,
but in the name of סומכוס, Sumchos, who is a student of
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, they said: No, גדולים חייבים קטנים פטורים, gedolim
chayavim ketanim peturim, only adults, not minors, you cannot bring a case
against a minor. Now the גמרא Gemara is going to go through
a whole discussion of can you bring a case against minors, you
know, מקבלין עדות שלא בפני בעל דין, mekablin eidush shelo bifnei ba'al
din, can accept testimony and so on. What I want to point
out... At the beginning is that there's a normally of course we
would never say that if somebody came and said I have a
שטר shtar that says or I have witnesses that say, you know,
that their father lent me a $10,000 and I want to bring
it, of course we would say no, you got to wait till
the kids are adults and that they can defend themselves. You know,
maybe we would appoint an אפוטרופוס, aputropis, but you know, somebody to
represent them, but why would we do that? That would only be
to their detriment, you know, there's whole discussions but you could not
just bring, you know, witnesses if you had some claim against an
estate and the other side was minors. However, here it's different because
here
it seems like it's understood that this object was known to be
yours. Maybe it was even known that the father stole it. So
in that case, it's a little more complicated. It's not like, you
know, you have your money, you have your estate, we all assume
that you own it and now I'm coming with some claim that
your father owes me a million dollars. No, it starts with a
different orientation. You're holding onto an object that was mine. Now, I
have to maybe prove it because you could claim your father bought
it or who knows what, but it starts with an orientation that
you're holding onto an object that was stolen from me and that
presumably is known, you know, and therefore the question is well, maybe
then we should just let me retrieve it, right? And maybe the
kids don't have a right to hold onto it and if they
have counterproof, let them bring it when they become adults. So let's
take a look. That seems to be why the rabbis would argue
on סומכוס Sumchos and say that you could bring, you know, you
could actually prosecute the case. Now we're going to have some actual
case law about this.
בר חמוה דרבי ירמיה, bar chamua de-Rabbi Yirmeyah, the son of the
father-in-law of רבי ירמיה, Rebbi Yirmeyah, טרך גלי באפי, tarach galla be-apei,
sort of slammed the door in the face of רבי ירמיה, Rebbi
Yirmeyah, of property בי דרבי ירמיה, bei de-Rabbi Yirmeyah, of רבי ירמיה.
Rebbi Yirmeyah. Now what happened was was that רבי ירמיה'ס Rebbi Yirmeyah's
father-in-law died,
רבי ירמיה'ס Rebbi Yirmeyah's
brother-in-law, his wife's brother
who inherited the father-in-law's estate, he said this is my property and
he wouldn't let רבי ירמיה Rebbi Yirmeyah in. רבי ירמיה Rebbi Yirmeyah
was claiming that he had purchased the property from the father and
רבי ירמיה Rebbi Yirmeyah wanted to go and seize the property, the
house or whatever it was, and the child, here he's underage, was
preventing him from entering and saying no, my father didn't sell it
to you, it's mine. אתא לקמיה דרבי אבין, ata lekamei de-Rabbi Avin,
he came to רבי אבין Rebbi Avin to prosecute this case or
to, you know, to try to get the property. אמר רבי אבין
amar Rabbi Avin said שלא
תובע. shelo tove'a. So the kid is demanding what's his. The father
died, it's presumed to now belong to the kid. So you can't
go ahead and just seize it. אמר ליה והמייתינא סהדי דאחזיקי בי
בחיי דאבוה, amar lei ve-ha maysina sahadi de-achziki bei be-chayei de-abuha, I'll
bring witnesses that I've established my ownership when the father was alive.
אמר ליה וכי מקבלין עדים שלא בפני בעל דין? amar lei ve-chi
mekablin edim shelo bifnei ba'al din? Do we accept witnesses where now
at the top of קט"ב עמוד ב, kuf yud beis amud beis,
not in the presence of the litigant of the other side? So
you can't go ahead and do that. He's a minor. So the
גמרא Gemara says ולא? ve-lo? Is that not true? והקתני בין גדולים
בין קטנים חייבים? ve-ha katania bein gedolim bein ketanim chayavim? We've got
the משנה, Mishna, the ברייתא Beraisa that says that you can retrieve
a stolen object from kids even if they're minors. So you see
you can prosecute a case against a minor. אמר ליה הרי מחלוקת
סומכוס בצדך. amar lei harei machlokes Sumchos be-tzidecha. So he said back
to whoever this was again, to רב חסדא Rav Chisda I think
it was, hold on, he said back to רבי ירמיה Rebbi Yirmeyah
except. He said back to רבי ירמיה, Rebbi Yirmeyah, he said,
yeah, but סומכוס Sumchos says you're not allowed to prosecute a case
against a minor. אמר amar, so רבי ירמיה Rebbi Yirmeyah said איכפל
כולי עלמא וקאי כסומכוס? ichpal kuli alma ve-ka'i ke-Sumchos? You're going to
fold up, you're going to like ignore the majority opinion and say
that oh, we're going to go like סומכוס Sumchos you're not allowed
to prosecute it לאפוקי לדידי lafukie lidi di to take away from
me my property? So why all of a sudden are we worried
about סומכוס? Sumchos? So now at this stage it sounds like רבי
ירמיה'ס Rebbi Yirmeyah's making a claim we can always prosecute a case
against minors. But let's take a look, we're not done yet. אדהכי
כי געגעיל מלתא אתו מטי לקמיה דרבי אבהו. ad hacha ki ga'agal
milsa aso mati lekamei de-Rabbi Abbahu. You know,
as this was sort of being litigated or discussed, debated whether you
could actually bring the case at all, the matter came in front
of רבי אבהו. Rebbi Abbahu. אמר רבי אבהו. amar Rabbi Abbahu. So
רבי אבהו Rebbi Abbahu said לא שמיע לכו הא דרבי יוסף בר
חמא אמר רבי אושעיא? lo shemi'a lechu ha de-Rabbi Yosef bar Chama
amar Rabbi Oshaya? Did you,
have you not heard the teaching of רבי יוסף בר חמא Rebbi
Yosef bar Chama in the name of רבי אושעיא? Rebbi Oshaya? דאמר
רבי יוסף בר חמא אמר רבי אושעיא תינוק שתקף בעבדיו וירד לתוך
שדה של חבירו, de-amar Rabbi Yosef bar Chama amar Rabbi Oshaya tinok
she-takaf be-avadav ve-yarad le-soch sadei shel chaveiro, if an infant, whatever, a
young kid took his, you know, underage, took his servants and went
into somebody else's field. You know, he went to his next-door neighbor's
house and he had his servants there to back him up and
ואמר שלי ve-amar sheli and he, you know, and he built a
fence around it and he laid claim to it, he basically said
look, this is all mine, you know, he was claiming that it
belonged to him. מה ההלכה? ma ha-halacha? What's the הלכה? halacha? אין
ממתינין לו עד שיגדיל אלא מוציאין מידו מיד. ein mamtinin lo ad
she-yagdil ela motzi'im mi-yado mi-yad. We don't say we wait till he
grows up, but
you immediately retrieve from his hand immediately. Give the field back to
the person who we know to whom it belongs, וכשיגדל יביא עדים
ונראה, ve'chish'yigdal yavi edim ve'nir'eh, and when he grows up, then we'll
bring עדים edim and then we'll deal with it when he grows
up. So this seems to be you do adjudicate a case against
a minor because you're restoring the field. So that should show you
that we do adjudicate the case. So let's see what it says.
I'm sorry, excuse me, excuse me. It says, wait, hold on a
second. I said that right. So in this case, we're willing to
deal with a case against minors and retrieve this property, whereas not
in the case of Rabbi Yirmiya. Obviously, there is, so if you're,
excuse me, so if you're willing to do it here,
then why should we not be willing to adjudicate this case here
with the minor, says Rabbi Yirmiya, or
says Rabbi Abba to defend Rabbi Yirmiya. But there's an obvious huge
difference here and now we're finally getting to the heart of the
matter. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמי דמי, ami domi,
how can you compare them? התם, hasam, הוא דמפקינן מיניה דלא קיימא
ליה חזקה דאבוה. hu de'mafkinan minei d'lo kayma lei chazaka d'avuh.
Over there, we're taking the property out of the hand of this
guy, kid, who went with his servants and seized
the next-door neighbor's field, because he has
no relationship, he has no חזקה, chazaka, no presumption of ownership that
it was not in his father's possession that he now inherited. So
here, it's basically like this kid grabbed this property, get out of
here. You want to claim you own it? Well, you the kid,
wait till you're an adult and you'll bring, but we restore the
situation to the way it was before you made this type of
claim.
That's that case. We just restore the situation because to the person
who is מוחזק muchzak in the field. אבל היכא דאית ליה חזקה
דאבוה, aval heicha d'is lei chazaka d'avuh, but in the case of
Rabbi Yirmiya, where his brother-in-law basically is the presumed heir of the
estate, in that case, the status quo is that it's under the
possession or the presumed status quo under the possession of his brother-in-law.
In that case, לא, lo, we wouldn't say it. Which basically means
that do you deal with a case when a minor is involved?
It's like we want to keep things sort of at the status
quo. So the issue, and then if we want to deal with
the minor, we'll wait till the minor becomes an adult. So the
issue by the גזילה gezeilah is, on the one hand, you could
say, look, everybody knew this was my object, that's the status quo.
So even if the kids are minors, I should be able to
prove it's my object and retrieve it. That's the position of the
רבנן. rabanan. That's why there they say we will do it with
minors. Whereas סומכוס Sumchus says no, right now the status quo, it's
by
מטלטלין, metaltelin, and things that are chattel, it's fundamentally is assumed to
be in the possession of a person whose possession it's in, owned
by the person whose possession it's in. So even if we knew
it was yours, the status quo is that it's in the possession
of the kid. And therefore, you, if you want to change that
status quo, you have to wait till the kid grows up. In
the case of Rabbi Yirmiya, in that case, it was in the,
by land, it's presumed to be in the possession of the person
who owned it prior, and that person died, so now it's presumed
to be in the possession of the kid. And since that's the
status quo, sorry Rabbi Yirmiya, you cannot bring witnesses against the status
quo, you can't bring witnesses against a kid
if that's coming to disrupt the status quo. And finally, in the
case where the kid went and seized the next-door neighbor's field, so
we push away the kid and we say, you can't change the
status quo, and if you want to, wait till you're an adult.
So common denominator is we keep the status quo and if you
want to change it, you wait till the kid is an adult.
And the debate of סומכוס Sumchus and the חכמים chachamim seems to
be a debate of how we consider what we consider the status
quo to be. Okay, let's do a little bit more. אמר רב
אסי אמר רב שבתאי, amar Rav Assi amar Rav Shabtai, מקבלין עדים
שלא בפני בעל דין. mekablin edim she'lo bifnei ba'al din. You will
sometimes accept witnesses not in the presence of the other side. תהא
בה רבי יוחנן, t'hah bah Rabbi Yochanan, Rabbi Yochanan was astounded. וכי
מקבלין עדים שלא בפני בעל דין? ve'chi mekablin edim she'lo bifnei ba'al
din? What do you mean? We don't do that. Can you really
do that? קבלה מיניה רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, kiblah minei Rabbi Yosi
b'Rabbi Chanina, Rabbi Yosi b'Rabbi Chanina understood that he was talking about
a case כגון שהיה הוא חולה או עדיו חולים או שהיו עדיו
מבקשים לילך למדינת הים. kegon she'hayah hu choleh o adav cholim o
she'hayu adav mevakshim leilech l'medinat hayam. Basically in a case when there
was a real urgency and you might lose your evidence without it.
The guy who's bringing the case is sick, and sick meaning might
die, so he has a right to have his case heard even
if the other guy isn't around. Or the witnesses might die. Or
the witnesses were going on a trip and they might not be
able to be retrieved. So there would be sometimes in which we
would allow it, but then it has an additional criteria. ושיגרו לו
ולא בא, ve'shigru lo v'lo ba, and the other side was given,
they sent after him and said we have to bring this case
right
now because there's an urgency and the guy refused to show up.
In that case,
he blew it. Normally we'll see later you give him a long
time before you start. prosecute before you start doing the case not
in his presence, but when there is this urgency, he gets one
warning and then you will go forward with the case. תוספות Tosafot
thinks, suggests that maybe that's or he did not come, but the
simple reading is and he did not come. There's an urgency, you
give the guy a chance, he has one chance to show up,
if he doesn't then you move on with it.
Okay, אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel מקבלין
עדים שלא בפני בעל דין. mekablin edim shelo bifnei ba'al din. You
do accept witnesses, or at least there are times where you will.
אמר מר Amar Mar וכדידי מפרש לי מיניה דשמואל, v'khididi mefaresh li
minei d'Shmuel, to me it was explained that teaching of שמואל Shmuel
כגון דפתחו ליה בדינא k'gon d'patekhu leh b'dina that you began the
court
case ושלחו ליה ולא אתא, v'shalkhu leh v'lo ata, maybe he was
there when you started it and now you're trying to continue the
case and now he's refusing to come and to show up for
the following of the proceedings. Okay, and in that case again he's
to blame, it's different than the previous case because here you actually
began it. So here his refusal to come when summoned is enough
to allow you to continue handling the case. אבל
לא פתחו ליה בדינא, aval lo patekhu leh b'dina, but if you
did not begin the case, מצי אמר ליה matzi amar leh אנא
לבי דינא גדולה אזלינא, ana l'vei dina gadola azlina, he could actually
say, no, you know, even I'm refusing to come because I want
to go to the major בית דין Beit Din in ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
And people have the right to demand that they have their case
heard by that major בית דין, Beit Din, so until this case
started his non-coming actually would not allow you to prosecute the case
because he could always say I don't want it to be heard
in this בית דין. Beit Din. תוספות Tosafot has an interesting question
if that's just the right of the party being sued or even
the right of the party suing, can they demand to go to
בית דין Beit Din or does that give too much power in
the right of the party suing because if they have the money
to do that then they can basically threaten people and you know
get a settlement because people don't have the money to go to
ירושלים Yerushalayim and to defend themselves, which as we know is a
general problem in the system in general. Okay, things like that about
how people with the money that can last out court cases have
much more of an advantage. Anyway, אי הכי ei hakhi says the
גמרא, Gemara, one minute, if the person has the right to demand
to switch to the בית דין הגדול Beit Din HaGadol so כי
פתחו ליה נמי מצי אמר ליה לבי דינא גדולה אזלינא, ki patekhu
leh nami matzi amar leh l'vei dina gadola azlina, even if they
began the court case he has the right to switch venues, which
is a big חידוש, chiddush, you would say no, once you've accepted
this venue you can't switch it. But the גמרא Gemara says he
has the right. So even if he doesn't show up, you know,
he could say I want to switch go to the major בית
דין, Beit Din, not any venue but the major בית דין. Beit
Din. And therefore that would not give you a right to accept
witnesses not in his presence. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבינא
כגון דנקיט דיסקא מבי דינא גדולה. Amar Ravina k'gon d'nakit diska mibei
dina gadola. We're talking that the court has given authority from the
בית דין הגדול Beit Din HaGadol
so you know that they should deal with this case. Okay, so
in that case, now if that's true then even before they were
פותח בדין, pote'akh b'din, you know he couldn't go to the בית
דין הגדול Beit Din HaGadol because the בית דין הגדול Beit Din
HaGadol said that this court should hear it. But anyway it's not
exactly clear how the גמרא Gemara is drawing that line but presumably
you know before he opened the case then that court didn't have
authority but once he opened it and the court had authority and
maybe they were backed by the בית דין Beit Din then he
could no longer switch venues and then his refusal to come gives
us a right to continue the proceedings without him. Okay,
אמר רב, Amar Rav, we'll just do a little bit more, מקיימין
את השטר שלא בפני בעל דין. mekaymin et hashtar shelo bifnei ba'al
din. You can do קיום שטר. kiyum shtar. A שטר shtar is
signed and you want to just validate the witnesses, either the witnesses
themselves are testifying to that signature or other people are
around you know who know the signature, you don't need the בעל
דין ba'al din there. You already have a signed document. You are
not starting some new case, you're just proving that the signatures are
genuine. That's not like a דין din against somebody and you can
do that. רבי יוחנן אמר אין מקיימין את השטר שלא בפני בעל
דין. Rabbi Yochanan amar ein mekaymin et hashtar shelo bifnei ba'al din.
You can't. אמר ליה רב ששת לרב יוסף בר רב איבו, Amar
leh Rav Sheshet l'Rav Yosef bar Rav Ibu, אסברה לך טעמיה דרבי
יוחנן. asbera lakh ta'ameih d'Rabbi Yochanan. Let me explain you the reason
of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. אמר קרא Amar kra והועד בבעליו ולא
ישמרנו. vehu'ad biva'alav v'lo yishmerenu. You were warned the owners by a
goring ox and then they don't watch it, the ox. אמר רחמנא
Amar rachmana יבא בעל השור ויעמוד על שורו. yavo ba'al hashor v'ya'amod
al shoro. The owner of the ox has a right to come
and stand on his ox when his ox is being testified against.
You have a right to face your accusers even if they're only
accusing your money. So this is the principle of that you don't
do a court case against somebody when they're not present. Of course
that's nice to quote the פסוק, passuk, but the point here really
is, come on, the שטר shtar already has accepted witnesses on it
and you are just validating it. אמר amar רבא, Rava: and this
we'll read this last line for now, הלכתא מקיימין את השטר שלא
בפני בעל דין. hilkhata mekaymin et hashtar shelo bifnei ba'al din. You
can do it. Okay, and then the גמרא Gemara will continue on
and but the reason you can do it is obviously קיום שטרות
kiyum shtarot is fundamentally rabbinic, דאורייתא d'Oraita any signed שטר shtar is
assumed to be genuine and therefore it's really not like you're opening
a court case against somebody when you already have a signed שטר.
shtar. Okay, we will end here.